I'm a man who's trying to live from his heart,
أنا رجل أحاول العيش بقلب كبير،
and so just before I get going,
وقبل أن أتابع حديثي،
I wanted to tell you as a South African
أود أن أخبركم كوني من جنوب أفريقيا
that one of the men who has inspired me most
أن أحد الرجال الذين ألهموني جدا
passed away a few hours ago.
قد توفي قبل ساعات.
Nelson Mandela has come to the end
وصل نيلسون مانديلا إلى نهاية
of his long walk to freedom.
مسيرته الطويلة نحو الحرية.
And so this talk is going to be for him.
لذا، فهذه المحادثة ستكون من أجله
I grew up in wonder.
لقد كبرت في عالم من الخيال.
I grew up amongst those animals.
ترعرعت بين هذه الحيوانات.
I grew up in the wild eastern part of South Africa
ترعرعت في براري الجانب الشرقي لجنوب إفريقيا
at a place called Londolozi Game Reserve.
في مكان يدعى محمية لوندولوزي جايم.
It's a place where my family has been
حيث كانت عائلتي تعمل
in the safari business for four generations.
في مجال السفاري لأربعة أجيال متتالية.
Now for as long as I can remember,
على ما أذكر،
my job has been to take people out into nature,
كان عملي دائما يتمحور حول أخذ الناس في جولات في الطبيعة،
and so I think it's a lovely twist of fate today
لذا فإنني أعتقد الآن أنه كان قدرا جميلا اليوم
to have the opportunity
أن أتيحت لي الفرصة
to bring some of my experiences out in nature
أن أجلب بعضا من تجاربي في الطبيعة
in to this gathering.
لأتقاسمها معكم.
Africa is a place
لازالت أفريقيا مكانا
where people still sit under starlit skies
حيث يتمتع الناس بسماء مرصعة بالنجوم
and around campfires and tell stories,
في المخيمات متحلقين حول النار يروون الحكايات،
and so what I have to share with you today
وما أود أن أتقاسمه معكم اليوم
is the simple medicine of a few campfire stories,
هو ذلك الدواء البسيط المستوحى من القصص المروية،
stories about heroes of heart.
قصص أبطال يسكنون القلوب.
Now my stories are not the stories
القصص التي سأرويها لكم اليوم ليست بالقصص
that you'll hear on the news,
التي تسمعون عنها في الأخبار،
and while it's true that Africa is a harsh place,
وعلما بأنه من الصحيح أن أفريقيا مكان قاس،
I also know it to be a place
أعلم أيضا أنها مكان
where people, animals and ecosystems
حيث يعلمنا البشر والحيوانات والنظم الإيكولوجية
teach us about a more interconnected world.
أن نكون عالما أكثر ترابطا.
When I was nine years old,
عندما كنت في التاسعة من عمري،
President Mandela came to stay with my family.
أتى نلسون مانديلا ليمكث لدى عائلتي.
He had just been released from his 27 years of incarceration,
كان قد أُطلِق سراحه للتو بعد 27 سنة من السجن،
and was in a period of readjustment
وكان في مرحلة استيعاب وتأقلم
to his sudden global icon status.
مع وضعه الجديد كأيقونة عالمية.
Members of the African National Congress
اقترح بعض أعضاء المؤتمر الوطني الافريقي
thought that in the bush
أنه في الأدغال
he would have time to rest and recuperate
سيحظى مانديلا ببعض من الوقت ليستريح و يستعيد قواه
away from the public eye,
بعيدا عن الأضواء،
and it's true that lions tend to be
ومن المعلوم أن الأسود تميل إلى
a very good deterrent to press and paparazzi.
ردع الصحافة و المصورين بشكل جيد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it was a defining time for me as a young boy.
لكنه كان وقتا فارقا بالنسبة لي كفتى يافع.
I would take him breakfast in bed,
كنت آخذ طعام الإفطار إلى غرفة نومه،
and then, in an old track suit and slippers,
وكان يذهب مرتديا بذلة رياضية وشبشبا،
he would go for a walk around the garden.
ليتمشى في أرجاء الحديقة.
At night, I would sit with my family
وفي المساء، كنت أجلس مع عائلتي
around the snowy, bunny-eared TV,
حول جهاز التلفاز ذي الصورة المشوشة مع هوائي يشبه أذني الأرنب،
and watch images of that same
لنشاهد صورا
quiet man from the garden
لهذا الرجل الهادىء في الحديقة
surrounded by hundreds and thousands of people
و قد تحلق حوله المئات بل الآلاف من الناس
as scenes from his release were broadcast nightly.
حيث كانت لقطات إطلاق سراحه تبث مساء.
He was bringing peace
لقد كان يجلب السلام
to a divided and violent South Africa,
لجنوب إفريقيا التي كانت مقسمة وعنيفة
one man with an unbelievable sense of his humanity.
رجل واحد ذو روح إنسانية لا تصدق.
Mandela said often that the gift of prison
كان مانديلا دائما يقول أن الهدية التي أهداه إياها السجن
was the ability to go within and to think,
كانت القدرة على اكتشاف دواخله والتفكير،
to create in himself
والبدء بخلق الأشياء
the things he most wanted for South Africa:
التي يتمناها لجنوب إفريقيا بداخله أولا:
peace, reconciliation, harmony.
السلام والتصالح والانسجام.
Through this act of immense open-heartedness,
ومن خلال هذا العمل الذي قام به بقلب كبير مفتوح للجميع،
he was to become the embodiment
كان قد أصبح رمزا
of what in South Africa we call "ubuntu."
لما نطلق عليه في جنوب أفريقيا "أوبونتو".
Ubuntu: I am because of you.
أوبونتو تعني: أنا ما أنا عليه بسببك.
Or, people are not people
أو بمعنى آخر، الناس ليسوا أناسا
without other people.
من دون الآخرين.
It's not a new idea or value
ليست فكرة أو قيمة جديدة
but it's one that I certainly think at these times
لكنني أعتقد جازما أنها إحدى القيم
is worth building on.
التي تستحق أن نبني عليها في هذا الوقت بالذات.
In fact, it is said that in the collective consciousness of Africa,
ففي الواقع، من خلال الوعي الجماعي لإفريقيا،
we get to experience the deepest parts
أتيحت لنا الفرصة لتجربة الجوانب العميقة
of our own humanity
لإنسانيتنا
through our interactions with others.
من خلال تفاعلنا مع الآخرين.
Ubuntu is at play right now.
نحتاج إلى أوبونتو الآن.
You are holding a space for me
فأنتم الآن تحتفظون بمكان لي
to express the deepest truth of who I am.
لكي أفصح لكم عن ماهيتي الحقيقية.
Without you, I'm just a guy talking to an empty room,
من دونكم، فأنا شخص يتحدث إلى غرفة فارغة،
and I spent a lot of time last week doing that,
ولقد أمضيت وقتا طويلا الأسبوع الماضي أفعل هذا،
and it's not the same as this.
لكن الأمر مختلف تماما الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If Mandela was the national and international embodiment,
إذا كان نيلسون مانديلا أيقونة وطنية وعالمية،
then the man who taught me the most
فإن الرجل الذي علمني الكثير
about this value personally was this man,
عن هذه القيمة بشكل شخصي، هو هذا الرجل،
Solly Mhlongo.
سولي ملونجو.
Solly was born under a tree
رأى سولي النور تحت شجرة
60 kilometers from where I grew up in Mozambique.
على بعد 60 كلم حيث ترعرعت في الموزمبيق.
He would never have a lot of money,
لم يكن لديه الكثير من المال قط،
but he was to be
لكنه كان
one of the richest men I would ever meet.
أحد أغنى الناس الذين التقيتهم في حياتي.
Solly grew up tending to his father's cattle.
ترعرع سولي راعيا لماشية والده .
Now, I can tell you, I don't know what it is about people who grow up looking after cattle,
الآن يمكنني أن أقول لكم، ليست لدي أدنى فكرة عما يعنيه الأمر بالنسبة للناس الذين يعتنون بالماشية،
but it makes for über-resourcefulness.
لكنه أمر يجعل المرء واسع الحيلة والدهاء.
The first job that he ever got in the safari business
أول عمل حصل عليه سولي في مجال السفاري
was fixing the safari trucks.
كان إصلاح مركبات السفاري.
Where he had learned to do that out in the bush
أين تعلم فعل هذا في الأدغال؟
I have no idea, but he could do it.
لسيت لدي أدنى فكرة، لكنه يستطيع فعل هذا.
He then moved across into what we called
ثم بعدها انتقل إلى الجوار، إلى ما نسميه
the habitat team.
فريق السكنى.
These were the people on the reserve
حيث يوجد مجموعة من الناس بالمحمية
who were responsible for its well-being.
مكلفون بالعناية بها.
He fixed roads, he mended wetlands,
كان يصلح الطرق، والأراضي الرطبة،
he did some anti-poaching.
قام ببعض حملات مكافحة الصيد غير المشروع.
And then one day we were out together,
في أحد الأيام خرجنا سويا،
and he came across the tracks of where a female leopard had walked.
صادف شاحنة حيث دخلت أنثى نمر.
And it was an old track,
كانت شاحنة قديمة،
but for fun he turned and he began to follow it,
ومن أجل التسلية، قام بتعقبها
and I tell you, I could tell by the speed
وأقول لكم، من خلال السرعة
at which he moved on those pad marks
التي تحرك بها لتعقب آثارها
that this man was a Ph.D.-level tracker.
أن هذا الرجل حاصل على درجة دكتوراه في التعقب.
If you drove past Solly
إذا كنت تقود متقدما عن سولي ،
somewhere out on the reserve,
في مكان ما في المحمية،
you look up in your rearview mirror,
و نظرت إلى المرآة العاكسة،
you'd see he'd stopped the car
فستراه و قد أوقف سيارته
20, 50 meters down the road
على بعد 20 أو 50 مترا على الطريق
just in case you need help with something.
في حالة احتجت للمساعدة.
The only accusation I ever heard leveled at him
الاتهام الوحيد الذي سمعته قد وُجِّه له،
was when one of our clients said,
كان من أحد الزبناء حين قال،
"Solly, you are pathologically helpful."
"سولي أنت خدوم بشكل مَرَضي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I started professionally guiding people
عندما بدأت أزاول مهنيا دوري كدليل
out into this environment,
آخذ الناس في جولات في البيئة،
Solly was my tracker.
كان سولي سائق مركبتي.
We worked together as a team.
كنا نعمل كفريق واحد.
And the first guests we ever got
وكان أول ضيوفنا على الإطلاق
were a philanthropy group from your East Coast,
مجموعة من أعضاء أعمال خيرية من الساحل الغربي الأمريكي،
and they said to Solly, on the side, they said,
قالوا لسولي، على هامش الحديث، قالوا له،
"Before we even go out to see lions and leopards,
"قبل أن نذهب لرؤية الأسود و النمور،
we want to see where you live."
نريد زيارة بيتك حيث تعيش."
So we took them up to his house,
فأخذناهم إلى بيته،
and this visit of the philanthropist to his house
وكانت زيارة هذه المجموعة إلى بيته
coincided with a time when Solly's wife,
قد صادفت تلك الفترة حيث كانت زوجة سولي،
who was learning English,
التي تتعلم اللغة الإنجليزية،
was going through a phase where she would open the door
تمر بتلك المرحلة حيث تفتح الباب
by saying, "Hello, I love you.
قائلة: "مرحبا، أحبك.
Welcome, I love you." (Laughter)
أهلا، أحبك." (ضحك)
And there was something so beautifully African
كان هناك شيئ رائع خاص بأفريقيا
about it to me, this small house
بالنسبة لي، هذا البيت الصغير
with a huge heart in it.
بداخله قلب كبير.
Now on the day that Solly saved my life,
في ذلك اليوم الذي أنقذ فيه سولي حياتي،
he was already my hero.
كان قد أصبح بطلي.
It was a hot day,
كان يوما حارا،
and we found ourselves down by the river.
وجدنا أنفسنا بجانب النهر.
Because of the heat, I took my shoes off,
وبسبب الحرارة، كنت قد نزعت حذائي،
and I rolled up my pants,
وطويت أطراف سروالي،
and I walked into the water.
ودخلت إلى الماء.
Solly remained on the bank.
ظل سولي على الضفة.
The water was clear running over sand,
كان الماء صافيا يجري على طبقة من الرمل،
and we turned and we began to make our way upstream.
فعرجنا لنسلك طريقنا نحو أعلى النهر.
And a few meters ahead of us,
وعلى بعد أمتار منا،
there was a place where a tree had fallen out of the bank,
كان هناك مكان حيث توجد شجرة وقد تداعت على الضفة،
and its branches were touching the water,
وكانت أغصانها تلامس الماء،
and it was shadowy.
وكانت ظليلة.
And if had been a horror movie,
ولو كنا في فيلم رعب،
people in the audience would have started saying,
لبدأ المتفرجون في القول،
"Don't go in there. Don't go in there." (Laughter)
"لا تذهب هناك، لا تذهب هناك " (ضحك)
And of course, the crocodile was in the shadows.
وبطبيعة الحال، كان هناك تمساح في الظل.
Now the first thing that you notice when a crocodile hits you
أول ما تلحظه حين يهاجمك تمساح
is the ferocity of the bite.
هي شراسة عضته.
Wham! It hits me by my right leg.
"هآآم" !! كان قد هاجم قدمي اليمنى.
It pulls me. It turns. I throw my hand up. I'm able to grab a branch.
جرني للأسفل وأدارني، رميت بيدي للأعلى. تمكنت من التقاط غصن.
It's shaking me violently.
كان يهزني بعنف.
It's a very strange sensation
كان إحساسا غريبا
having another creature try and eat you,
أن ترى مخلوقا آخر يحاول أكلك،
and there are few things that promote vegetarianism like that.
لذا فهناك ما يعزز التوجّه النباتي، كهذا الحادث مثلا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Solly on the bank sees that I'm in trouble.
سولي على الضفة يرى أنني في خطر.
He turns. He begins to make his way to me.
استدار. وبدأ يسير في اتجاهي.
The croc again continues to shake me.
لازال التمساح يهزني.
It goes to bite me a second time.
يحاول عضي للمرة الثانية.
I notice a slick of blood in the water around me
لاحظت بقعة دم في الماء حولي
that gets washed downstream.
ينظفها تيار النهر تباعا.
As it bites the second time, I kick.
مع عضته الثانية، أحاول ركله
My foot goes down its throat. It spits me out.
فتصل قدمي إلى حلقه، فيبصقها.
I pull myself up into the branches,
فأسحب نفسي نحو الأغصان،
and as I come out of the water, I look over my shoulder.
لحظة خروجي من الماء، نظرت فوق كتفي.
My leg from the knee down
تبدو قدمي أسفل ركبتي
is mangled beyond description.
مشوهة بشكل يفوق الوصف.
The bone is cracked.
العظم مهشم.
The meat is torn up.
واللحم ممزق.
I make an instant decision that I'll never look at that again.
حينها اتخذت قرارا فوريا بأن لا أنظر إلى قدمي مرة أخرى.
As I come out of the water,
وبينما أنا أخرج من الماء،
Solly arrives at a deep section,
يصل سولي إلى الشطر العميق من النهر،
a channel between us.
إلى قناة بيننا.
He knows, he sees the state of my leg,
إنه يعلم ، ويرى الحال التي عليها قدمي،
he knows that between him and I
ويعلم أن بيني وبينه
there is a crocodile,
يوجد تمساح،
and I can tell you this man doesn't slow down for one second.
وأقول لكم، أن هذا الرجل لم يتوان للحظة واحدة.
He comes straight into the channel.
عبر القناة بدون تردد.
He wades in to above his waist.
خاض الماء إلى أن وصل إلى منتصف جسمه.
He gets to me. He grabs me.
وصل إلي والتقطني.
I'm still in a vulnerable position.
كنت لا أزال في موقف ضعف.
He picks me and puts me on his shoulder.
أخذني ووضعني على كتفه.
This is the other thing about Solly, he's freakishly strong.
هذه ميزة أخرى لسولي، أنه قوي بشكل فظيع.
He turns. He walks me up the bank.
يستدير، ويأخذني إلى الضفة.
He lays me down. He pulls his shirt off.
يمددني على الأرض، ينزع قميصه.
He wraps it around my leg,
يلف به قدمي،
picks me up a second time,
يحملني مرة أخرى،
walks me to a vehicle,
ويأخذني إلى السيارة،
and he's able to get me to medical attention.
استطاع سولي أن يقدم لي الرعاية الطبية الضرورية.
And I survive.
وها أنا ذا على قيد الحياة.
Now — (Applause)
الآن --(تصفيق)
Now I don't know how many people you know
الآن ، لا أدري كم هو عدد الأشخاص الذين تعرفونهم
that go into a deep channel of water
الذين يخوضون قناة مائية
that they know has a crocodile in it
يعلمون أن بها تمساحا
to come and help you,
ليقوموا بمساعدتكم،
but for Solly, it was as natural as breathing.
لكن بالنسبة لسولي، فالأمر كان طبيعيا كالشهيق والزفير.
And he is one amazing example
لقد كان مثالا رائعا
of what I have experienced all over Africa.
عن كل تجاربي في أنحاء إفريقيا.
In a more collective society,
في مجتمع أكثر تآلفا،
we realize from the inside
ندرك من داخلنا
that our own well-being is deeply tied
أن سعادتنا مرتبطة بشكل عميق
to the well-being of others.
بسعادة الآخرين.
Danger is shared. Pain is shared.
الخطر مشترك، الألم مشترك.
Joy is shared. Achievement is shared.
الفرح مشترك. النجاح مشترك.
Houses are shared. Food is shared.
البيوت مشتركة. الطعام مشترك.
Ubuntu asks us to open our hearts
تحثنا قيمة "أوبونتو" على فتح قلوبنا
and to share,
وعلى المشاركة،
and what Solly taught me that day
وما علمنيه سولي ذلك اليوم
is the essence of this value,
هو روح هذه القيمة،
his animated, empathetic action
من خلال عمله الجريء والمتعاطف
in every moment.
في كل لحظة.
Now although the root word is about people,
مع أن أصل الكلمة مرتبط بالإنسان،
I thought that maybe ubuntu was only about people.
كنت أعتقد أن كلمة أوبونتو ربما مرتبطة فقط الإنسان.
And then I met this young lady.
عندها التقيت بهذه الشابة.
Her name was Elvis.
كان اسمها إلفيس.
In fact, Solly gave her the name Elvis
في الواقع، سولي من أعطاها هذا الإسم
because he said she walked like she was doing
لأنه قال أنها تمشي و كأنها
the Elvis the pelvis dance.
ترقص رقصة الخصر لإلفيس بريسلي.
She was born with very badly deformed back legs and pelvis.
لقد ولدت بعيب خلقي على مستوى القوائم الخلفية و الحوض.
She arrived at our reserve from a reserve
جاءت إلى محميتنا من محمية
east of us on her migratory route.
تقع على الشرق في طريق هجرتها.
When I first saw her,
حين رأيتها أول مرة،
I thought she would be dead in a matter of days.
ظننت أنها ستموت في غضون أيام.
And yet, for the next five years
لكن، لمدة 5 سنوات
she returned in the winter months.
كانت تعود في شهور الشتاء.
And we would be so excited to be out in the bush
وكنا دائما متحمسين للذهاب إلى الأدغال
and to come across this unusual track.
لنصادف هذا المسار غير العادي.
It looked like an inverted bracket,
كانت تبدو كقوس مقلوب،
and we would drop whatever we were doing and we would follow,
وكنا نترك ما بأيدينا مهما يكن لنذهب و نتبعها،
and then we would come around the corner,
لنتتبعها من الزاوية،
and there she would be with her herd.
فنراها هناك مع قطيعها.
And that outpouring of emotion
ونلمس تلك المشاعر المتدفقة
from people on our safari trucks
من مرتادي السفاري على مركباتنا
as they saw her, it was this sense of kinship.
حين ينظرون إليها، كانت تلك مشاعر الألفة.
And it reminded me
فيذكرني هذا
that even people who grow up in cities
أنه حتى من ترعرعوا في المدن
feel a natural connection
يشعرون بتلك الصلة الطبيعية
with the natural world and with animals.
مع عالم الطبيعة والحيوانات.
And yet still I remained amazed that she was surviving.
ومع كل هذا، مازلت مندهشا أنها لا زالت على قيد الحياة.
And then one day we came across them at this small water hole.
وذات يوم، صادفناهم عند حفرة مائية صغيرة.
It was sort of a hollow in the ground.
كانت أشبه بتجويف على الأرض.
And I watched as the matriarch drank,
وكنت أشاهد الفيلة الأم وهي تشرب،
and then she turned in that beautiful slow motion of elephants,
بعدها استدارت بذلك البطء الجميل المعهود لدى الفيلة،
looks like the arm in motion,
وكأنه عرض بطيء لحركة الأذرع،
and she began to make her way up the steep bank.
وبدأت تسلك طريقها نحو الضفة المنحدرة.
The rest of the herd turned and began to follow.
استدار بقية القطيع فبدأوا بالالتحاق.
And I watched young Elvis
ورأيت الصغيرة إلفيس
begin to psych herself up for the hill.
وهي تحاول دفع نفسها نحو المرتفع.
She got visibly -- ears came forward,
تحركت أذناها نحو الأمام بشكل واضح،
she had a full go of it and halfway up,
هي مستعدة تماما وقد قطعت نصف الطريق نحو الأعلى،
her legs gave way, and she fell backwards.
انزلقت قوائمها، فتراجعت إلى الخلف.
She attempted it a second time,
أعادت الكرة ثانية،
and again, halfway up, she fell backwards.
مرة أخرى، وصلت إلى منتصف الطريق، فتدحرجت إلى الخلف.
And on the third attempt,
وفي المحاولة الثالثة،
an amazing thing happened.
حصل أمر مدهش.
Halfway up the bank,
في منتصف الطريق نحو الضفة،
a young teenage elephant came in behind her,
جاء فيل يافع من خلفها،
and he propped his trunk underneath her,
فربط خرطومه بخرطومها،
and he began to shovel her up the bank.
وبدأ يجرها نحو أعلى الضفة.
And it occurred to me
فعلمت حينها
that the rest of the herd
أن بقية القطيع
was in fact looking after this young elephant.
كانوا بالفعل يهتمون بهذه الفيلة الصغيرة.
The next day I watched again
في اليوم الموالي،
as the matriarch broke a branch
رأيت الفيلة الأم وهي تقطع غصنا
and she would put it in her mouth,
فكانت تضعه في فمها،
and then she would break a second one
ثم تكسر غصنا آخرا،
and drop it on the ground.
وتضعه على الأرض.
And a consensus developed between all of us
ولقد كونا إجماعا فيما بيننا
who were guiding people in that area
نحن من نأخذ الناس في جولات في المنطقة
that that herd was in fact moving slower
أن القطيع بالفعل يتحرك ببطء
to accommodate that elephant.
ليتماشى مع خطوات الفيلة الصغيرة.
What Elvis and the herd taught me
إذا فما علمتني إياه إلفيس و القطيع
caused me to expand my definition of ubuntu,
جعلني أوسع تعريفي لكلمة أوبونتو،
and I believe that in the cathedral of the wild,
وأننا في كاثدرائية الغابة،
we get to see the most beautiful parts of ourselves
تكون لدينا الفرصة لرؤية الجوانب الجميلة فينا
reflected back at us.
وقد انعكست علينا مرة أخرى.
And it is not only through other people
ليس فقط من خلال الناس
that we get to experience our humanity
نختبر إنسانيتنا
but through all the creatures that live on this planet.
بل من خلال كل المخلوقات التي تعيش على هذا الكوكب.
If Africa has a gift to share,
إن كانت لأفريقيا أية نعمة لتتقاسمها معنا،
it's a gift of a more collective society.
فهي نعمة مجتمع أكثر تآلفا.
And while it's true that ubuntu is an African idea,
ومع أن أوبونتو تبقى فكرة إفريقية
what I see is the essence of that value
لكنني أرى روحها
being invented here.
وقد تمثلت هنا.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Pat Mitchell: So Boyd,
بات ميتشل : حسنا، بويد،
we know that you knew President Mandela
نعلم أنك تعرف الرئيس مانديلا
from early childhood
منذ طفولتك المبكرة
and that you heard the news as we all did today,
وأنك علمت بالخبر كما علمنا به جميعا اليوم،
and deeply distraught
بذهول كبير
and know the tragic loss that it is to the world.
ونعلم حجم الخسارة الكبيرة بالنسبة للعالم.
But I just wondered if you wanted
لكنني كنت أتساءل إن كنت تريد
to share any additional thoughts,
أن تتقاسم معنا أية أفكار إضافية،
because we know that you heard that news
لأننا نعلم أنك سمعت بالخبر
just before coming in to do this session.
قبيل عرضك لهذه المحادثة.
Boyd Varty: Well thanks, Pat.
بويد فارتي: حسنا،شكرا لك بات.
I'm so happy because it was time for him to pass on.
أنا سعيد جدا أن وقته قد حان للرحيل.
He was suffering.
لأنه كان يعاني.
And so of course there's the mixed emotions.
وبطبيعة الحال تخالجني مشاعر متناقضة.
But I just think of so many occurrences
لكنني أتذكره في عدة مواقف
like the time he went on the Oprah show
مثلا حين حل ضيفا على برنامج "أوبرا"
and asked her what the show would be about.
فسألها ماهو موضوع هذا البرنامج.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And she was like, "Well, it'll be about you."
فأجابته: "حسنا، موضوعه هو أنت."
I mean, that's just incredible humility.
أعني، أنه كان يتحلى بمنتهى التواضع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He was the father of our nation
كان أب أمتنا
and we've got a road to walk in South Africa.
ولدينا مسار طويل لنقطعه في جنوب إفريقيا.
And everything, they used to call it Madiba magic.
كان الجميع يطلق عليه لقب ماديبا الساحر.
You know, he used to go to a rugby match and we would win.
أتعلمين، كان يحضر مبارايات الكرة المستطيلة وكنا نفوز.
Anywhere he went, things went well.
أينما حل، تجري الأمور بشكل جيد.
But I think that magic will be with us,
لكنني أعتقد أن سحره سيظل معنا،
and the important thing is that we carry
والشيء المهم، أن نحمل معنا
what he stood for.
ما ظل يناضل من أجله.
And so that's what I'm going to try and do,
وهذا ما سأحاول القيام به،
and that's what people all over South Africa are trying to do.
وهذا ما يحاول الناس في أرجاء جنوب إفريقيا القيام به.
PM: And that's what you've done today. BV: Oh, thank you.
ب.م: وهذا ماقمت به اليوم. بويد فاري: أوه .. شكرا جزيلا
PM: Thank you. BV: Thank you. Thanks very much.
ب.م: شكرا بويد فاري: شكرا. شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)